<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Books, Movies | Rohit Mishra]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/categories/books-movies/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-16T19:28:12+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rohit Mishra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Head First HTML With CSS and XHTML - Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2010/05/31/head-first-html-with-css-and-xhtml-review/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-31T11:50:06+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2010/05/31/head-first-html-with-css-and-xhtml-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Head First HTML with CSS &amp; XHTML was my second book in Head First series after <a href="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/hf-html.jpg"><img src="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/hf-html.jpg" alt="Head First HTML" /></a>Head First Java, 2nd Edition. Like the 1st book, this book continues the method of simple, redundant explanations that make the content stick.</p>

<p>The book doesn&rsquo;t cover all the topics but really makes sure that the reader has completely understood the topics being taught. The conversational tone of the book is great if you are learning XHTML and CSS on your own.</p>

<p>If you are getting started with web-designing, this book is highly recommended.</p>

<p>You can buy the <a href="http://http://www.flipkart.com/head-first-html-css-xhtml-book-8184040822/head-first-html/1?affid=INRohitblo">book from Flipkart</a> for Rs. 440.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[De Dana Dan Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/11/27/de-dana-dan-review/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-27T22:20:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/11/27/de-dana-dan-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>De Dana Dan is a pathetic movie with no story and little comedy. Very boring. Don&rsquo;t watch it. <br/>
It is the most stereotype comedy and before interval , all that happens is the preparation for a comedy background. All Priyadarshan wants us to do is keep track of mistaken identities and the room numbers that they have to put up in a hotel in the movie. There are very few scenes of the trio of Akshay, Sunil and Paresh Rawal together. Akshay is locked out of action for one hour in the movie. <br/>
It is a complete waste of time and money. Sit somewhere with friends and chat. That will have much more humor.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Terminator Salvation Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/11/25/terminator-salvation-review/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-25T00:40:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/11/25/terminator-salvation-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Terminator 2: Judgement Day is my favorite movie. The third part &ndash; Rise of the Machines was  a bad sequel which an ardent follower like me also didn&rsquo;t like. Arnold had become old and it was sad to know that Judgement Day did come. That is why Terminator Salvation was important. Christian Bale carries the legacy of John Connor ahead. I would have loved to see what happens after Judgement Day to Connor. What we get is a Connor who is hailed as the Prophet of the Resistance against Skynet. How the young teen changed into the fighting machine is not shown at all?</p>

<p>The lack of detail is appalling in other places too. Sam Worthington&rsquo;s character Marcus &ndash; a test robot made by Cybernet is great. But I must concede that Transformers had better visual effects. That is not the movie&rsquo;s strength. Its core lies in the human vs. machines dialogues &ndash; the ones by Kyle Reece and Connor are strong.</p>

<p>Salvation gives you the feeling that it was made with the intention that there is more to come. The story has to move ahead. I am waiting for the next installment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story Behind Neoforma.com]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/03/22/the-story-behind-neoforma-com/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-22T15:01:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/03/22/the-story-behind-neoforma-com</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/ScYPX-d-hfI/AAAAAAAAAJs/_wECAAxfFUk/s1600-h/starting+something.png"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/ScYPX-d-hfI/AAAAAAAAAJs/_wECAAxfFUk/s320/starting+something.png" alt="" /></a><br/>
Browsing through the &ldquo;World Trade&rdquo; section of <a href="http://www.vit.ac.in">VIT</a> library, I was looking for C.K.Prahalad&rsquo;s famous &ldquo;The Fortune at the Bottom of the Pyramid&rdquo;. To my despair, someone had misplaced that book. Disappointed, I glanced over the adjacent Entrepreneurship section - a permanent favorite. I found <a href="http://www.ravel.tv/startingsomething.html">&ldquo;Starting Something&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/ppl/webprofile?action=vmi&amp;id=38796802&amp;authToken=767B&amp;authType=name&amp;trk=ppro_viewmore&amp;lnk=vw_pprofile">Wayne McVicker</a>&ndash; a strange name. I thought it will be a &lsquo;how-to&rsquo; book on starting a company. It turned out to be a biography of the founder of a Silicon Valley &lsquo;dotcom&rsquo; company &ndash; Neoforma.com I had read a lot about dotcom companies and their bust, so I picked it up to know something more about it.</p>

<p>As I started reading it, one thing instantly became clear. This book was not about Wayne McVicker; it was about Neoforma.com - a company that he had co-founded with his friend Jeff. The book showed how two people passionate about a business opportunity went on to make a company worth $ 3 billion in 4 years battling against the mightiest Venture Capital firm &ndash; <a href="http://www.kpcb.com/">Kliener Perkins</a>. Starting Something has all characters &ndash; good, bad and nasty, but all of them come across as very real. It gives us an unflinching look into both the drak and bright sides of corporate culture &ndash; where dreams are fulfilled and the best of friendships are broken. Denis Coleman &ndash; founder of Symantec Corporation (the makers of the very popular Norton Antivirus sums up the book</p>

<blockquote><p>A must read for aspiring entrepreneurs. It took me years in the trenches building Symantec to learn the people-side lessons so freely elucidated by McVicker - and unfortunately not yet taught in business schools.</p></blockquote>

<p>&ndash; that is how deep the book goes in exploring the importance of people in the success of a business.</p>

<p>The book is divided into numerous small chapters of 4 to 5 pages generally. That gives fluidity to the story &ndash; the events register their presence, but it becomes clear that no single event can become the center-piece of the narrative.</p>

<p>Wayne McVicker and his friend Jekk Kleck weren&rsquo;t the typical Silicon Valley entrepreneurs &ndash; both were in their late thirties with a family to care for. Like most other founder pairs, Wayne and Jeff weren&rsquo;t the best of friends from the outset. But, both strongly believed in the concept of better flow of information to buyers &ndash; in this case hospitals. They wanted to provide all possible information about the large medical equipments as well as numerous small products that occupy hospital rooms. As their belief in the usability and importance of the idea grew with time, they ran into confrontation with their bosses at <a href="http://www.varian.com">Varian </a>&ndash; their present company. As Varian resisted, Jeff and Wayne proposed to carve out a spin-off from Varian. Though successful , they were taken aback to see the bickering and hateful corporate environment under which they left the company they had been working for years.</p>

<p>The book moves on to show how Neoforma discovered internet and realized the immense potential of the medium. As the company grew, Wayne explains his dilemma in hiring new people- which continues even as Neoforma transformed into a behemoth. He concludes that the single most important factor is the actual fit between the company and the employee.</p>

<p>Starting Something is not only about the business part of it. As Wayne and his wife Anni put every piece of their asset on mortgage for Neoforma with 2 young children to care for, Wayne describes the emotional tug-of-war  he went through while eliminating their complete security putting their entire lives on the fate of Neoforma.</p>

<p>The book is also about people &ndash; from Jack (their warm attorney) to Wally and Shawn (their angel investors) To Alexander, JP and Bret (their VCs) Wayne explicitly highlights his ambivalence about venture capitalists &ndash; the people who care only about one single thing - making money and making it fast.</p>

<p>Throughout the book, Wayne never makes an attempt to cover-up his emotions. How he felt uncomfortable from being a founder to donning the role of an investor in the company that he had made himself. He also discusses his insecurity as Neoforma changes from CDROMs to a complex website - a technology he was unfamiliar with.</p>

<p>The book&rsquo;s richness comes from the part where Wayne analyzes his own actions - why he pursued a particular deal, why he was adamant to hire a particular man to why he considered himself completely unsuitable in running Neoforma in the long run.</p>

<p>You will fell that the narrative becomes similar to a movie as the nook proceeds &ndash; not flashy in t he same way but with similar ulterior motives and huge drama at play.</p>

<p>After a successful IPO and a severe crash in share prices, Wayne realized that Neoforma had outgrown him. He moves on to found <a href="http://www.attania.com">Attania</a> &ndash; but not with the same intensity as Neoforma. That intensity is now for his family.</p>

<p>Overall a higly recommended read. You will love the truth and reality of the story.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dostana -- Its Good]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2008/11/15/dostana-its-good/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-15T22:08:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2008/11/15/dostana-its-good</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SSBI3t70FRI/AAAAAAAAAIU/orQDGtAYsfk/s1600-h/800px-Dostana.jpg"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SSBI3t70FRI/AAAAAAAAAIU/orQDGtAYsfk/s320/800px-Dostana.jpg" alt="" /></a><br/>
This post was written on Saturday but due to connection problems, I wasn&rsquo;t able to publish it.</p>

<p>After the debacle called my Math Semester examination (more on it in the next post), I actually went out and saw a movie. Yeah, times have changed as Mom said &ldquo;It looks like you are into an engineering college now. Going for the movie on Day 1 of your semesters.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I have a strong dislike for movie analysts and experts. The basic criterion for the dislike is the fact that if you end up watching each and every movie that is made, how can you enjoy it!! And yeah, we do appreciate good plots and every other technicalities, but the point is that when you are in the theater, are you engrossed in the story or wondering about what this character or the plot could have shaped up? I had the plan of writing a review on Dostana and so when I was watching the movie, I was making some sort of mental notes on it. Its inescapable.</p>

<p>Ok. A hell lot of theory on movie reviews. Now lets move on to Dostana. The movie opens up with a Shilpa Shetty dance number. The song&rsquo;s good. But, I have never been a big fan of hers. Though you have to say that she&rsquo;s looking good. My friends were gasping from the first scene onwards. What is more attractive is John!! Man, his look wil put Troy&rsquo;s Brad Pitt to shame. As the whole movie revolves around a gay love story, I can take the chance of calling him hot. John &ndash; a photographer and Abhishek &ndash; a nurse end up at Priyanka&rsquo;s home looking for a room in Miami. (Thats a place to workThey end up making a gay love story because Priyanka&rsquo;s masi won&rsquo;t allow two baba log to live with baby. The story is very predictable. Both end up loving Priyanka and do their best to break her courtship with the boss at her fashion mag &ldquo;Bobby Deol&rdquo;. And as the movie ends, Priyanka goes to Bobby leaving John and Abhishek. Only in a movie!!</p>

<p>Now, Priyanka is looking deliriously hot, sexy, beautiful, put in the adjective of your choice. I am not competent to talk about acting in a forceful tone but, I will only say that she did great in all those happy moments. And thankfully, there  weren&rsquo;t that many sad moments in the movie to deal with. Priyanka, it felt good to see you back in your beautiful groove. (Haven&rsquo;t watched Fashion till now, but friends say she&rsquo;s better over here.</p>

<p>Abhishek surely looks the more authentic gay. His comic timing is impeccable. Although not the hunk like John, there is some mysterious sexiness inherent in him. His clothing, look, everything is great. He is in the character of the imperfect person, afraid of horror movies, slapped by his mother, &hellip;.. and does it well. John is first-of-all hot, but there&rsquo;s nothing new for him in the movie. It was a kind-of-repeat of John in &ldquo;Garam Masala&rdquo;. But, yes he looks the part and is a very suitable cast for the role. Kirron Kher goes bonkers when she discovers that her son is uhoh gay. The song &ldquo;Ma tera munda bigar gaya&rdquo; is a  comic mad. The whole theater went mad with laughter. Her dialogues like &ldquo;Mere ko pata nahi ki tu meri bahu he ya damad ( I don&rsquo;t know whether you are my son-in-law or my daughter-in-law)   are comical epic stuff. Bobby as Priyanka&rsquo;s boss looks as ordinary as he always does. We kept wondering why Karan didn&rsquo;t use his Filmfare Most Powerful stuff and rope in some dude like Hrithik for the role. Basically, Bobby&rsquo;s part is the movie&rsquo;s not-so-glorious one.</p>

<p>Overall, its a must-watch movie, if you want to just have fun, There is no big story, but the movie does it. And yes, you won&rsquo;t find a movie where two mainstream actors John &amp; Abhishek are in a lip lock.  It was aaaarghhhhhh. How could they? So much for reality depiction.</p>

<p>What, looking for a rating or what? This is no self important bloke talking. And I can&rsquo;t rate a movie by watching it once.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
