<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: India | Rohit Mishra]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/categories/india/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-27T02:06:28+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rohit Mishra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Silence of Our Heroes]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2013/05/28/silence-of-heroes/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-28T22:42:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2013/05/28/silence-of-heroes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5445/8871609083_a9ff11b31c_z.jpg" alt="World Cup 2011 champions" /></p>

<p>In India, most of our heroes come from cricket. This is not because other fields have not produced as many great exponents, but due to the disproportional love and attention that cricket enjoys. There is nothing as common in all parts of our country as much as the love for the game of cricket. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I read somewhere that it is good to see your heroes from a distance. If you get too close, you can then see that they have a lot of the same deficiencies that we have. In the past 6 years, thanks to IPL, we have seen a lot more of our cricketing heroes than we used to see earlier. But, I must contend, that for people like me - who saw a lot of cricket right from childhood - our heroes came from international cricket. <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>There is something unique about becoming a hero in sports. It takes a long time to become one and once you become one, you stay there. Mahendra Singh Dhoni is arguably the newest hero, and he made his ODI debut in December, 2004. <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> Also, talk to anyone who grew up in 70s and 80s, and it won&rsquo;t take much before they start raving about the likes of Sunil Gavaskar and Kapil Dev.</p>

<p>If you would do a poll of Indian cricketing heroes, the list would generally include Sachin Tendulkar, Sunil Gavaskar, Kapil Dev, Rahul Dravid, Sourav Ganguly, Mohinder Amarnath, Anil Kumble and Mahendra Singh Dhoni. This is not an exhaustive list by any measure, but I believe that most of these names will feature in everyone&rsquo;s own list of heroes.</p>

<h2>The 2013 IPL spot-fixing/betting controversy</h2>

<p>Indian cricket and IPL have been rocked in the past few weeks by  allegations of spot-fixing and betting. First came the spot-fixing expose by the Delhi Police. The fact that most T20 matches are won or lost by minuscule margins meant that these 3 rotten apples &ndash; Sreesanth, Chandila and Ankeet Chavan - were basically doing their best to help their team - Rajasthan Royals - lose. So, I do not understand how spot-fixing and match-fixing are different in the context of T20 cricket?</p>

<h2>Dravid</h2>

<p><img src="http://farm5.staticflickr.com/4085/5070363687_f651727137_z.jpg" alt="Rahul Dravid | Credit: Royal Challengers Bangalore/Flickr" ></p>

<p>I saw the first press conference that Delhi Police did after arresting these three players live on TV. The Police played recordings of matches and showed how these 3 bowlers were deliberately bowling bad deliveries. What stuck with me was the sight of Rahul Dravid in all these tapes, anguished by his bowlers getting ripped apart.</p>

<p>Dravid took the underdog <em>moneyball</em> <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> team of Rajasthan Royals to the playoffs this season with a great display of captaincy and getting the best out of the limited resources he has. To know that these 3 cheats were letting down such a great man was more painful than their act of cheating itself.</p>

<p>Dravid has always been the selfless hero of Indian cricket ready to do whatever the team needed of him. Whenever India&rsquo;s opening pair failed, or we needed a wicket-keeper batsmen before Dhoni came on, the team turned to Dravid. If you put the word cricket and gentleman together, most followers of the game world over will think of Dravid.</p>

<p>The former English international Ed Smith said in a <a href="http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/557122.html">beautiful profile of Dravid</a> in ESPNCricInfo -</p>

<blockquote><p>In that sense, Dravid is a true gentleman. Where many sportsmen flatter to deceive, Dravid runs deep. He is a man of substance, morally serious and intellectually curious. For all his understatement, he couldn&rsquo;t fail to convey those qualities to anyone who watched him properly.</p></blockquote>

<p><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3326/3493343617_a773010387.jpg" alt="Dravid and Laxman after their famous partnership at Eden Gardens 2001"></p>

<p>Dravid has always been a batsmen defined by his determination. His performances have been extra-ordinary, yet subtle. His partnership with Laxman in the 2001 Eden Gardens Test against Australia was surreal. When playing in pace-friendly pitches of England, Australia or South Africa, it was always Dravid on whom the team primarily depended. <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/2011/aug/24/the-spin-rahul-dravid?CMP=twt_gu">This account of his batting by Andy Bull in The Guardian</a> in the England test-series of 2012 which India lost 4-0 is a great read.</p>

<p>There is something else about Dravid. He is a cricketer who I have learned to appreciate as I have grown up. He is not the most flashy or fast-scoring batsmen. It takes time for one to understand the class of this man.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qr4bK63WxXY&amp;feature=player_embedded">This speech</a> that he gave at Sir Donald Bradman Oration 2011 is a must to understand how deeply this man cares for the game.</p>

<p>It is not surprising then that among all the greats, it is only Dravid who has taken a <a href="http://www.thehindu.com/sport/ipl2013/dravid-insists-on-finding-the-truth-to-restore-sanity/article4749636.ece">dignified stance</a> in the whole betting/fixing saga. He said how he was pained by the fixing scandal and thinks IPL needs some cleaning up. This may not sound much but when put against the deafening silence of his contemporaries, it is a lot.</p>

<h2>Dhoni</h2>

<p><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/8879316324_3d56f3a56d.jpg" alt="Mahendra Singh Dhoni"></p>

<p>Among this list of cricketing heroes, Dhoni is the only one I can claim to have seen from the start of his career. Dhoni is an inspiration in how he has reached where he has. He wasn&rsquo;t the best wicket-keeper or the most fluent batsmen when he started his career. But he has worked hard and been a charismatic captain of his teams. Though most heroes are a mix of talent and effort, in Dhoni&rsquo;s case, the proportion of effort is much higher.</p>

<p>Dhoni is also in a way symbolic of the rise of the part of India to which I belong. Dhoni is a native of Ranchi and went to the same high school that my girlfriend went to. There was not even a cricket stadium in Ranchi, when he grew up and the Bihar/Jharkhand Ranji team was not a fancied domestic team. In his meteoric rise to the apex of Indian cricket, Dhoni symbolises the hope of the majority of Indians who do not live in the tier-1 cities.</p>

<p>While I was at college, my parents moved to Ranchi. On a trip home, my Dad took me to see Dhoni&rsquo;s parents&#8217; home where he grew up. It is a typical small-town government quarter. The only difference was a Hummer standing in front and a bunch of policemen who gladly take up the role of tour guides and tell you stories of Dhoni. I doubt if anyone visiting Ranchi does not  see the impact of this man on the city - from the stories about him to the shops named after him.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2867/8879367658_fbb439a8f3.jpg" alt="Dhoni's winning shot at the 2011 World Cup final"></p>

<p>It was under Dhoni and with his own performance in the final that India won the 2011 World Cup. That was one of the high points of a life for most of us. The Test World Number 1 ranking, T20 World Cup, CB Series and his remarkably consistent performance as captain and player for the Chennai Super Kings in IPL make him one of the most successful Indian cricketers.</p>

<p>Apart from his huge list of achievements, Dhoni is famous for his calm demeanour in the most tense of matches. In this context, the last few days have been horrible for those who consider him a hero. When India was white-washed 8-0 in Australia and England, the selectors wanted to replace Dhoni but they were <a href="http://sports.ndtv.com/india-vs-england-2012/news/200562-bcci-blocked-dhonis-removal-as-captain">stopped by the board.</a> There was a controversy at the time - the Board President M Srinivasan is the owner of Chennai Super Kings, the team Dhoni leads in IPL.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> Now, as CSK team principal and Srinivasan&rsquo;s son-in-law Gurunath was arrested by Mumbai Police for betting, along with Vindoo Dara Singh ( another fixer ) with whom Dhoni&rsquo;s wife Sakshi saw IPL matches this season, Dhoni has maintained silence - skipping press meets. Moreover, Dhoni is a Vice President of India Cements.</p>

<p>Yesterday, in a press conference before the Indian team left for Champions Trophy in England, Dhoni <a href="http://www.thehindu.com/sport/ipl2013/dhoni-is-gagged-as-crickets-politicians-close-ranks/article4760355.ece">did not answer</a> any single question related to this controversy. He gave a cool smile as the media manager of BCCI prevented journalists from asking Dhoni questions about this controversy.</p>

<p>As Srinivasan has mounted a brazen defence full of lies - declaring Gurunath to be <strong>an enthusiastic fan only</strong>, one wonders why Dhoni is not speaking out. Why one of the most successful Indian captains is letting a board of liars and cheats gag him? The troubling counter-side is that he is deliberately avoiding these difficult questions. I am sure Dhoni&rsquo;s fan base will be sky high as always and this controversy will be forgotten as days go on. Either Dhoni is not brave enough to take on the board or is complicit with them in this farce. As days go on, one will have to accept the inevitable that we will never find out the truth. The integrity of a national hero will forever be compromised.</p>

<h2>Gavaskar, Srikanth, Kapil, Kumble</h2>

<p>Gavaskar and Srikanth have both vaguely defended the board president&rsquo;s position on different TV channels with arguments which will make your bones grimace. Kapil Dev has not spoken a word. Kumble made a weird suggestion of removing <em>all records</em> of the 3 Royals players, but spoke nothing about the CSK episode.</p>

<p>All these legends of the game are associated with BCCI as commentators, committee members and team mentors. It is puzzling that none of them comes out and speaks against these corrupt administrators who are ruining a game that all of them made famous.</p>

<p>As Rajdeep Sardesai said on his news show last night, it seems that all of these legendary players have become servile to BCCI and that the Board has bought their silence by giving them plush and financially rewarding positions.</p>

<p>Like Dhoni, each of them have a support base of tens of millions of fans, and huge amount of money. What stops them from holding the board accountable. Or have they turned in to businessmen who just use the game just as any broadcaster or advertiser uses the game?</p>

<h2>Sachin</h2>

<p><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3757/8879152467_c6e1b11c53_z.jpg" alt="My Facebook post with Sachin with the World Cup"></p>

<p>Whatever little memories I have of my childhood, a lot of them involve Sachin. The Sharjhah double centuries against Aussies, the century against Kenya in the 1999 World Cup after his father died, the 2003 match against Pakistan in World Cup to count off the top of my mind.</p>

<p>Till the time I believed in praying, I would have said 10x prayers for Sachin than for everything else combined. When <a href="http://shikhasinghiitkgp.blogspot.in/2011/03/endulkar-dare-we-imagine-unimaginable.html">The Times of India published a front=page piece called Endulkar</a> predicting his end in 2006, I stopped reading ToI. I have not forgiven ToI for that yet.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5463/8879469843_0a082ec84e.jpg" alt="Sachin plays well, India sleeps well"></p>

<p>Unlike Dravid, who I learnt to appreciate, I have been a fan of Sachin as far back as my memory goes. There were times I wished he would just stay at the non-strikers end. Never get out. When he was <a href="http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/496743.html">accused of ball tampering</a>, one felt being personally accused of cheating. The anger at that time would outdo the best of shouting matches on our news channels today.</p>

<p>Sachin&rsquo;s brilliance, technique, style &ndash; I guess a lot of us would have got our PhDs if all the discussion we did on him was counted for. Sachin has retired from ODIs and IPL. He may retire from tests soon. When that happens, I know a lot of us will divide our lives in pre-Sachin (retirement) and post-Sachin phases. I doubt we would root for someone ever again as we do for Sachin.</p>

<p>I often wonder what would happen if Sachin took a stance on some political issue. He rarely does. He rarely talks about things other than cricket. In the finals of this year&rsquo;s IPL, Sachin came on the mike and chatted with Harsha Bhogle. It was awesome to hear him speak. I may tune in to matches to hear his commentary, as I did to hear Dravid&rsquo;s. But, I hope he does not turn in to the meek character that Gavaskar has become. We survived all of Sachin&rsquo;s nervous 90s. We won&rsquo;t survive that.</p>

<h2>BCCI</h2>

<p>BCCI is a private body which runs cricket in India but is accountable to no one. The people at the top of BCCI - the likes of Dalmiya, Srinivasan, Jaitley, Pawar and Shukla - have been there for decades. All of these men have much bigger companies to run or are sitting members of the Parliament. The state associations are completely dependent on the BCCI for their funding, getting allocated a match or their members being sent overseas as managers.</p>

<p>This cycle of sycophancy, corruption and brazen impropriety is ruining our game. Inevitably, every on-field action is now seen with  suspicion. The Board and its shameless masters keep their grip over the game feeding on the love we bestow to our heroes and our game.</p>

<p>One wonders why these heroes, these demigods do not do anything to get the game out of the clutches of these people. I am sure all of them know more of the devious ways of the cricket board than we do. Most of them are connected to the board. Why let this feudal parasitic structure keep a deathly grip on all of cricket in this country. The members of the board come from different political parties, so obviously none of the parties will ever talk of cleaning the game and its administration. Who else can do something to fix this murky situation?</p>

<p>Martin Luther King said:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;History will have to record that the greatest tragedy of this period of social transition was not the strident clamor of the bad people, but the appalling silence of the good people.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>These are not just good people. These are heroes to millions of people. Why stay silent?</strong></p>

<h3>Footnotes</h3>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Its quite telling that while discussing Mizoram&rsquo;s transition to peace from insurgency in his book &ldquo;<strong>India after Gandhi</strong>&rdquo;, the historian <strong>Ramachandra Guha</strong> says - &ldquo;By 1999 Mizoram had overtaken Kerala as India&rsquo;s most literate state. The integration with the mainland was proceeding apace; Mizos were learning the national language, Hindi, and watching and playing the national game, cricket.&rdquo;<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>IPL, on the other hand, has made many international players very famous in India. The likes of Chris Gayle, Michael Hussey, Lasith Malinga and Kieron Pollard are very popular here, whereas only the more avid cricket follower would know them otherwise. <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>No one among my friends would include Virat Kohli in this list of heroes as yet. He has a lot more to do to join this exclusive list.  <a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Dravid used the word &lsquo;money ball&rsquo; himself in a post-match presentation. When asked by the presenter whether this was a subtle way of putting the opposition in pressure, Dravid, true to his honest nature, said that this was a fact pointing the stark difference in the budgets of his team and his then-rivals the Chennai Super Kings, and the Mumbai Indians.  <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Srinivasan often says that he does not own CSK. He is only a shareholder of India Cements which owns CSK. But, he is the majority shareholder of India Cements. If you thought making stupid opinions in public with a lot of force was only the domain of politicians, Srinivasan will prove you wrong. <a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>The fact that Times of India has gone on to become mostly a tabloid newspaper helps. <a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dear Arvind, Please Chuck the Cap and the Rhetoric]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/10/08/dear-arvind-please-chuck-the-cap-and-the-rhetoric/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-08T05:28:45+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/10/08/dear-arvind-please-chuck-the-cap-and-the-rhetoric</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many Indians, I have great hopes from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arvind_Kejriwal">Arvind Kejriwal</a>.  He seems ambitious, genuine and fresh. He has all the makings of a leader that we have been desperately looking for. His entry in active politics is one of the rare good things to happen in Indian politics lately.</p>

<p>However,  Kejriwal needs to transform himself from an activist to a leader. I didn&rsquo;t agree with his <a href="http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/team-anna-member-arvind-kejriwal-health-worsens-fast-entered-day-8/1/211253.html">&lsquo;fast-unto-death&rsquo;</a> for getting Lokpal Bill passed. As Dr. B.R. Ambedkar said, Indians should quit strikes and anshans in favor of  constitutional methods. Arvind&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.hindustantimes.com/India-news/NewDelhi/Kejriwal-associates-burn-Delhi-electricity-bills/Article1-941179.aspx">call to people of Delhi</a> to not pay electricity will achieve little beyond making headlines. India is paying heavily for populist economics, via subsidies and inefficient government programs. We don&rsquo;t want a new leader to continue with the same populist pandering that the old political class has done forever.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/acorn/status/254936984018120704">http://twitter.com/acorn/status/254936984018120704</a></p>

<p>Kejriwal <a href="http://iacmumbai.org/web/index.php/news-media/241-arvind-kejriwal-begins-civil-disobediance-movement-protest-delhi-power-hike">says that</a> the power tariffs were to be slashed, but weren&rsquo;t due to the nexus between the Delhi Government and the private power operators. His claims may be true, and he should build public opinion, expose this nexus instead of doing gimmicks like burning bills in front of the media.</p>

<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_244&rdquo; align=&ldquo;aligncenter&rdquo; width=&ldquo;650&rdquo;]<a href="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/kejriwal-6500210.jpg"><img src="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/kejriwal-6500210.jpg" alt="Kejriwal with his new cap" /></a> Kejriwal with his new cap[/caption]</p>

<p>Also, Kejriwal should stop wearing his iteration of the Gandhi-Anna Hazare cap. It is just a reminder of the farce that the other politicians do by sticking to starched white kurtas, invoking an unconscious connection with the leaders who fought for India&rsquo;s independence, while looting India of its resources. The common Indian that Arvind is trying to represent, doesn&rsquo;t wear a cap. Neither Arvind himself wore a Gandhi cap, till the launch of the Jan Lokpal movement.</p>

<p>In the mean time, we hear little from him on his views on reforms, FDI, foreign affairs, subsidies and other issues. He is not an anti-corruption activist only anymore. He is trying to become a mass leader. The mass needs to know what he thinks before it can trust him.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How the Government Is Fooling Us on the Question of Auctions]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/09/28/how-the-government-is-fooling-us-on-the-question-of-auctions/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-28T20:29:59+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/09/28/how-the-government-is-fooling-us-on-the-question-of-auctions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>India has had two major scams in the past few years - the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2G_spectrum_scam">2G spectrum scam</a> and the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_coal_allocation_scam">coal block allocation scam</a>. The 2G spectrum scam was ball parked in to a  range from $ 5 - 31 billions. The CAG report tabled in the Parliament pegged losses from coal block allocation at $33 billion.</p>

<p>On February 2, 2012, the Supreme Court <a href="http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2012-02-02/india/31016262_1_spectrum-licences-2g-spectrum-allotment-case">blew away the charade</a> put up by the Government, when it declared the spectrum allocation as <em>&ldquo;unconstitutional and arbitrary&rdquo;.</em> The Supreme Court quashed all the allocated spectrum licenses and <em> </em>asked the government to conduct fresh auctions.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile, the <a href="http://www.cag.gov.in/">Comptroller and Auditor General of India (CAG)</a> further blamed the Government for inefficient allocation of coal blocks. After the opposition complained about corruption, a CBI inquiry has been set up. The alleged coal allocation scam even involves the office of Prime Minister Manmohan Singh.</p>

<p>Many have argued why the government did not choose to auction scarce national resources like telecom spectrum and coal blocks in the first place. The Government sent a Presidential reference to the Supreme Court for clarification on its opinion on auctions. <a href="http://www.business-standard.com/india/news/auction-notonly-permissible-way-to-disposenatural-resources-says-sc/487902/">In an expected reply,</a> the Supreme Court said</p>

<blockquote><p>auctions are not the only permissible method for disposal of natural resources, across all sectors and in all circumstances.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.moneycontrol.com/news/business/fm-sibal-laud-sc-opinion-say-2g-auction-to-go-as-planned_762994.html">The Government is claiming its stand</a> has been vindicated that they were justified in not auctioning these resources in favor of common good. In a joint press conference few minutes back, the ministers for Finance, Telecom and Law stated how their stand was vindicated about not choosing auctions. They quoted various instances in the SC judgement which justified their opinion.</p>

<p>But, it is sad to see the Government put up another gimmick instead of accepting the blatant loot of resources that it allowed. The SC judgement on telecom spectrum made clear the corruption by A. Raja and several telecom executives. Many reports in the media have completely exposed the Government&rsquo;s claim of common good.</p>

<p>To say that auctions should be one and only route to distribute national resources would be unwise and intrusion of the policy  making powers of the Government. At the same time, the Government cannot wash off its hands from its responsibility to explain to the country what common good they saw in giving away scare resources to fly-by-night operators who in turn have made a huge profit by selling these resources in the open market. In this press conference, none of the ministers quoted this important part of the judgement.</p>

<blockquote><p>when such a policy decision is not backed by a social or welfare purpose, and precious and scarce natural resources are alienated for commercial pursuits of profit-maximising private entrepreneurs, adoption of means other than those that are competitive and maximise revenue may be arbitrary and face the wrath of Article 14 (right to equality) of the Constitution</p></blockquote>

<p>A smug Kapil Sibal, the Minister for Communications &amp; IT, didn&rsquo;t justify <a href="http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/todays-paper/article2325809.ece?ref=archive">his famous <strong>&ldquo;zero loss&#8221; </strong></a>in 2G spectrum allocation comment made last year before the SC judgement came.</p>

<p>Ordinary Indians still have faith in the higher judiciary. But, we should also be careful not to allow politicians to score points by interpreting a SC judgement to justify their nefarious motives.</p>

<p>NDTV&rsquo;s Sreenivasan Jain exposed the corruption in coal allocation both in the Congress and the BJP in his show &ldquo;Truth vs Hype&rdquo;. (<a href="http://www.ndtv.com/video/player/truth-vs-hype/truth-vs-hype-of-coal-gate-part-i/235426">Part 1</a> | <a href="http://www.ndtv.com/video/player/truth-vs-hype/truth-vs-hype-coal-gate-the-all-party-scam-part-ii/245145?pfrom=home-topstories">Part 2</a>) It clearly shows how the then Coal Secretary P C Parikh&rsquo;s call for transparent auction of coal blocks felt on deaf ears in the PMO, which stalled the policy change to the benefit of the companies which were granted coal blocks.   Part 2 shows the story of Subodh Kant Sahai, Union Tourism Minister from Jharkhand who lobbied for coal mines to be allotted to his brother&rsquo;s company. Also, a story from Chattisgarh showing how Coal-gate has been a bi-partisan scam with involvement from both the Congress and the BJP.</p>

<p>Considering the deep involvement of both the Congress and the BJP, it is highly unlikely that the Coal Scam will see a similar result as the 2G Scam unless the Supreme Court strictly directs the CBI. But, at the very least, we, the ordinary people of this country shouldn&rsquo;t fall in to the bait of these politicians who first facilitate these scams, and then justify their actions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Women in India]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/07/13/women-in-india/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-13T18:09:32+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/07/13/women-in-india</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of minutes after waking up this morning, this is <a href="http://www.ndtv.com/article/india/guwahati-s-shame-30-men-seen-molesting-girl-just-four-arrested-242840">what I saw</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VjiKPnt_LM0">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VjiKPnt_LM0</a></p>

<p>A 19 year old  Class 11 girl was beaten, stripped and molested on the streets of Guwahati while she was returning from a party at 10pm in the night. The shame of India is that a significant number of people will rationalize this incident by focusing on a girl partying, what she was wearing, who she was with, and not on what happened with her. Some news channel reporters shot this incident, and it went viral on the net. 96 hours have passed since the incident, and only 4 people from this mob have been arrested.</p>

<p>This is one of those animals -<a href="https://www.facebook.com/amar.jyotikalita.7">Amar Jyoti Kalita </a> who, from his Facebook profile, works at an Assam Govt. company called Amtron. He has apparently been arrested. If you can fuck his life, please do so. Thanks.</p>

<p>There is a sad truth about what happened - though it outrages and saddens me, it doesn&rsquo;t surprise me. Look at this Hindustan times headline on January 1, 2008 - <a href="http://www.hindustantimes.com/News-Feed/India/Mob-molests-2-women-on-New-Year-s-Day/Article1-266701.aspx">Mob molests 2 women on New Year’s Day</a> . This was on New Year&rsquo;s eve. The women, part of the same family, were returning after celebrating New Year at J W Mariott hotel, and were accompanied by <a href="http://www.expressindia.com/latest-news/Mob-Molestation-I-want-to-get-over-the-horror/257230/">one of the victim&rsquo;s husband</a>.  A year before that, something similar happened at the Gateway of India in Mumbai. Similar to today&rsquo;s incident, that too was recorded and circulated. Lot of outrage and anger followed. Some of those beasts, all teenagers, were  arrested. To my knowledge, none of the perpetrators were convicted or their conviction wasn&rsquo;t news-worthy.</p>

<p>Unlike most other things, one cannot blame this only on the government. Yeah, police response can be faster and they can go harder against these beasts, but one cannot expect the police to patrol all the streets all the time. The main problem is that when an average Joe sees an incident like this, he decides to walk away. Not help the victims, not call the police - just walk away. That is how 2 young people - <a href="http://www.ndtv.com/article/cities/keenan-reuben-case-accused-laughed-when-identified-150534">Keenan-Reuben</a>, died in Andheri, Mumbai last year when they fought people eve-teasing their girlfriends. Bystanders thought it was none of their business as the two were beaten to death.</p>

<p>What should one do? Not go out on the streets with girls. Carry guns all the time. The solution at the individual level are pretty trivial. This is where the government can do its due - frame tough laws, and hang these beasts. These people shouldn&rsquo;t be treated like humans. We should do what we do to animals who go crazy - shoot them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Need My Change]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/03/17/i-need-my-change/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-17T04:34:27+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2012/03/17/i-need-my-change</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/no-change.jpg"><img src="http://www.rohitmishra.me/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/no-change.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The second line translates to</p>

<blockquote><p>All shopkeepers give this [the candies] instead of a 50paise or 1 rupee coin.</p></blockquote>

<p>I came across <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=346364805406933&amp;set=a.300054006704680.67810.115989455111137&amp;type=1&amp;theater">this image</a> on Facebook . Like many others, I am also irritated by Â the replacement of good old 50p, 1 rupee coins with candies. I hear rumors that this is due to the apparent crisis of coins in circulation in the market. It may be true, or this may be a nice trick to increase the revenue of your friendly neighborhood Â shop.</p>

<p>Whatever, I can&rsquo;t wait for the next generation of mobile money to come here. Will <a href="https://squareup.com/">Square</a> be the answer?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
