<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Allotrop | Rohit Mishra]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/categories/allotrop/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-27T01:49:55+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rohit Mishra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[End of Allotrop]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2014/02/25/end-of-allotrop/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T00:02:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2014/02/25/end-of-allotrop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Despite my best efforts, <a href="https://allotrop.com">Allotrop</a> has not been able to attract enough user activity. So, after about 18 months of pursuing this dream, I have decided to move on. The product will stay online for the near future, but I will stop working on it.</p>

<p>I will write a more detailed post on what led me to Allotrop and the things I tried to make it work shortly.</p>

<p>I am extremely thankful to everyone who visited Allotrop and supported me online and offline. I also want to thank my family, especially my father who bankrolled my expenses for the past couple of years. I wish I had more to show for the faith he put in me. I am also extremely lucky to have a girlfriend who has often been the first person to try a new feature I developed and has helped me through all the lows of the past couple of years.</p>

<p>Death by obscurity is one of the worst ways for a startup to go down. I would have preferred being beaten comprehensively by a better product. But, we do not chose how we die, do we?</p>

<p>I will look for a full-time employment or freelance work now. I will also use this time to try out some new things I have not been able to play with for lack of time. Client side MVC frameworks, Scala, Go, Clojure, Node, iOS 7 and Android 4.4. I hope the delight of learning something new will tide over this gloom of failure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
