<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Education | Rohit Mishra]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-27T01:54:40+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rohit Mishra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SRCC, 100% and Academic Inflation]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2011/06/18/srcc-100-and-academic-inflation/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-18T15:20:55+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2011/06/18/srcc-100-and-academic-inflation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do you do when a joke turns into reality. You get confused. When a friend scores highly in an exam, we tease him or her by saying <em>you can only get a 100%. What will you do after that?</em> . This is a problem now. 100% is no longer a joke. One of India&rsquo;s famous colleges <a href="http://www.srcc.edu/">Sri Ram College of Commerce</a> wants students coming from a non-commerce stream to have <a href="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/education/Delhi-University-admission-Finally-the-100-cutoff-is-here/articleshow/8856031.cms">100% marks to be eligible</a> for a BCom course. This prompted the education minister Kapil Sibal(St. Stephens&#8217;, Harvard) to say how he would not have got admission in any good Indian college today. Lets not all start blaming SRCC. They are not the first.</p>

<p>The IITs have for a long time made a 6 hour entrance examination the universe-shaking moment for most of the under-20 youth in India. We Indians don&rsquo;t want to study engineering. We <em>only </em>want to go to an IIT. Colleges like SRCC are equivalent to IITs and IIMs, so it shouldn&rsquo;t be surprising that they also felt the need for something equally irrational.</p>

<p>In his famous <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/ken_robinson_says_schools_kill_creativity.html">TED talk in 2007</a>, Sir Ken Robinson talked about academic inflation - how something that needed a masters degree at a time, now needs a PhD and something that needed a PhD now needs a double PhD. Sir Ken also says that the entire public education system is a protracted process of university entrance. I will like to add job entrance to that. When I was in middle school, there was so much talk of learning and understanding. They were the end-goals. Today, even if we learn and understand, it is not for the thrill of learning but for the task of scoring high in the next examination.</p>

<p>[ted id=66]</p>

<p>As the SRCC story played across the media, a huge number of Indian parents must have shaken their head in despair that their child is only getting a 96%. Darwin would be elated.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tuition Mania]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/05/09/tuition-mania/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-09T21:14:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/05/09/tuition-mania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SgWnCt7H_BI/AAAAAAAAAKk/lSDagoGxf3k/s1600-h/tuition.jpg"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SgWnCt7H_BI/AAAAAAAAAKk/lSDagoGxf3k/s320/tuition.jpg" alt="" /></a><br/>
So what you and I always knew has now been verified by the Assocham &ndash; the Indian industry association. Private Tuition is rampant and costly all over the country. The <a href="http://business.rediff.com/report/2009/may/08/middle-class-spends-a-third-of-income-on-kids-tuition.htm">Assocham report</a> says :</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Private tuitions have witnessed a steep increase of about 40-45 per cent in the last few years as middle class parents have been spending nearly one-third of their monthly incomes on them.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>The problem with tuition is that it makes you dependent. Its like a cigarette &ndash; once you have started with it, you think you can&rsquo;t do without it.<br/>
So people go on from having tuition at school, then tuition for IIT and even then for IIM. The problem is that it undermines your regular education (though that itself is a farce Now parents are spending one-third of their incomes on these private tutors. Whats wrong folks!! Go and look for some creative thing for your child. Mugging up that chemistry table or that physics equation won&rsquo;t make him/her the next Einstein. If you really care so much about your child, work hard and break up from this self-supporting myth of tuition. <br/>
There is a lot that can be learnt today. More than your money-sucker tutor can ever teach.</p>

<p>Photo courtesy <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ming2046/">blurasis</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Locking Us in -- Present Sir!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/03/12/locking-us-in-present-sir/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-12T05:49:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2009/03/12/locking-us-in-present-sir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SbhfHKgt1BI/AAAAAAAAAJk/F1z5f39PQ9A/s1600-h/waiting+for+time+to+pass.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_djcir2GI86Q/SbhfHKgt1BI/AAAAAAAAAJk/F1z5f39PQ9A/s320/waiting+for+time+to+pass.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Photo courtesy <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/fake_eyes/342753239/">orange42</a> through Flickr<br/>
Teachers have been a great part of my life &ndash; often encouraging, loving and caring throughout my school life. They really made you want to come to school. You felt good, right!!</p>

<p>But coming to college, I have seen the other side of teachers. For me college was supposed to be &ldquo;freedom&rdquo;. But even in India where we pride ourselves for our democratic freedom, the word &ldquo;freedom&rdquo; has been made to carry negative annotations in our colleges.</p>

<p>Apart from the ultra-conservative practice of keeping boys and girls as separated as possible and locking us inside our hostel blocks at 9, the biggest restriction is the minimum attendance requirement of 75%. The biggest pain in my life now is the compulsion to go &amp; waste my 5 hours in class everyday. Waste because I neither like nor understand most of the things that are taught in classes. (And I am not alone. Go to any class and you will find most in a state of delusion &ndash; chatting, messaging, aimlessly taking down notes and gazing at their watches or cell phones to keep tracking how much more they have to take for the day. There will always be some who are listening very attentively &ndash; why they would even listen attentively to Bush talking about world peace. Thankfully, there are some classes which are good, but generally classes are a pain.</p>

<p>I wanted to go deeper and find some sense in this madness. Why colleges need a minimum attendance? Colleges provide us degrees after testing us on a minimum set of requirements &ndash; subjects and syllabus that they agree upon. For passing these subjects, why do they make attending classes necessary? Let the student do what he wants to &ndash; go to library, sit in lab or just play Counter-Strike in his room. The best thing will be that the college accepts the work that students want to do. All but a very few have some interest which they want to pursue, but drop because it will hurt their GPA. About attending classes &ndash; if I like the subject and if the teacher is good, I will attend the class. Otherwise, I will bunk it.</p>

<p>The college should be cool with it. The whole world is moving to a more personalized approach in life &ndash; and thats the way it should be with teaching too. College shouldn&rsquo;t only be restricted to attending &lsquo;x&rsquo; number of classes for &lsquo;y&rsquo; number of days. I should have complete autonomy on choosing what I want to learn and how I want to go about it.</p>

<p>Colleges and teachers must be brave enough to take this leap of faith. They may face only very few students in a classroom but at least all of them are there with a passion to learn. Let others choose or pursue their own passion. Ultimately, the aim is to help everyone achieve his/her best. Minimum restrictions will only help everyone do their best. The fear of misuse is present and is also valid, but smart techniques can easily correct most of them.</p>

<p>Start with something simple. Instead of giving assignments, where people just print-out the corresponding Wikipedia page or worse print and copy the content.A free way is the best and fastest approach to your destination, ain&rsquo;t it?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Am in a Rich College]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2008/12/06/i-am-in-a-rich-college/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-06T00:07:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://mishrarohit.github.io/blog/2008/12/06/i-am-in-a-rich-college</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Anyone who has been following me here or on twitter <a href="http://www.twitter.com/movingahead">(@movingahead)</a> will know the fact that Wifi is coming to <a href="http://www.vit.ac.in">VIT</a>. Unlike other colleges, even the most minuscule ones VIT till now thought internet access to be a taboo, so the only way to access net was to use a proxy in the labs or use a low speed, high cost . access like the one I am using now &ndash; the Plug2surf types.</p>

<p>Finally heeding to popular demand, Wifi is being introduced. So, I am happy. I should be, right!! The only problem is that I hadn&rsquo;t thought that I will have to pay Rs. 900 per month for this happiness. The Wifi is a paid one bandwidth from Reliance, device from Motorola and services by Vellore Online Systems. Hey!!! But what from VIT??</p>

<p>The plans offered start from Rs. 500 for a 256 Kbps 2 GB download limit connection. Another one is at Rs. 700 per month which is same speed but 3.5 GB limit. Now that much bandwidth is very less for a net addict like me &ndash; No I don&rsquo;t waste my time on porn!! There can be other more productive uses. The only plan that suits me is an unlimited plan for 900 at 384 Kbps. I think it would have been better if I also had a few oil wells in Kuwait to finance this education.</p>

<p>I am taking the 900 plan because Dad as always knows how much I am dependent on net for my updates. Proud to have such a father. But, still something lingers in my mind. A fear that I don&rsquo;t misuse this facility and an anguish that couldn&rsquo;t my university provide this wifi at subsidised rates.</p>

<p>When I came to VIT, it was famous for being one of the cheapest private engineering college in India. The truth is that colleges like Manipal and Jaypee rob you once. VIT with its media-savvy people robs you slowly in installments.</p>

<p>If this is the way private education will work in this country, wonder whether my posts on allowing international institutes in India were really correct!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
